{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "U.S. doctors worked with a dictator of this country to eradicate yaws. This country was\nevacuated by U.S. troops as the major effect of Franklin Roosevelt's \"good neighbor\" policy;\nRoosevelt claimed to have written this country's constitution. For 10 points, name this country\nwhere the U.S. intervened in 1994 to restore Jean-Bertrand Aristide to Port-au-Prince.",
      "answer": "Haiti"
    },
    {
      "question": "The first Church council named for this place endorsed ultramontanism and espoused the\ndoctrine of Papal infallibility. The second council named for this place introduced the vernacular\nmass and renounced anti-Semitism. For 10 points, identify this namesake of 1868 and 1962\nCatholic ecumenical councils, which is also the independent state where the Pope lives.",
      "answer": [
        "Vatican",
        "Vatican City"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "When applied to an entire country, this process is known as an \"interdict,\" which was notably\nused against England under King John. This process was applied to Holy Roman Emperor Henry\nIV, who had to kneel in the snow at Canossa to have it reversed by Pope Gregory VII. For 10\npoints, identify this process of withholding sacraments from a person who has offended Catholic\nlaw.",
      "answer": "excommunication"
    },
    {
      "question": "The city of Bagram was originally the capital of an ethnically Greek state that practiced this\nreligion. Two statues of this religion's founder at Bamiyan (pr. BAY-mee-yahn) were destroyed\nby the Taliban. For 10 points, name this religion whose Vajryana (pr. VAHJ-rye-AH-nuh) form\nis practiced in Tibet by followers of the Dalai Lama.",
      "answer": "Buddhism"
    },
    {
      "question": "A song of this kind derives its melody from \"La Montovana,\" the same folk song that is the\norigin of \"The Moldau\" (pr. MOLE-dow), and is called \"Hatikvah\" (pr. hah-TEEK-vuh).\nSongs of the kind include Jana Gana Mana (pr. jah-NAH guh-nuh MOO-nuh) and La\nMarseillaise (pr. MAHR-see-YEZ). For 10 points, identify this type of song, such as \"God Save\nthe Queen.\"",
      "answer": [
        "national anthems"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This position was first held by a man named St. Augustine who is not to be confused with the\none who wrote The City of God. This position was held by Justin Welby, who succeeded\nRowan Williams. For 10 points, name this religious position at the head of the Anglican Church,\nwhich is named for the city that was the destination of Chaucer’s pilgrims.",
      "answer": "Archbishop of Canterbury"
    },
    {
      "question": "According to this religion, a compass-like device called the Liahona (pr. LEE-uh-HOH-nuh)\nwas used to show an escape route from Jerusalem. Other artifacts of this religion include Urim\nand Thummim, the \"seer stones\" used to translate the golden plates which the angel Moroni\nrevealed to its founder. For 10 points, name this church founded by Joseph Smith.",
      "answer": [
        "Mormon church",
        "LDS",
        "Latter-Day Saints"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The Council of Trent mandated that Catholic realms adopt this standard, which did not arrive\nin Greece until 1923. It replaced an earlier standard named for Julius Caesar. When it was\nintroduced to Great Britain in 1751, monthly debtors cried \"give us back our eleven days.\" For\n10 points, identify this modern calendar named for the Pope who devised it.",
      "answer": [
        "Gregorian calendar",
        "Gregorian"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "(TIEBREAKER EXAMPLE QUESTION) This denomination was wracked by the Landmarkism controversy in the 1850s, shortly after it\nwas founded under the leadership of William Bullein Johnson. This denomination split off over\nthe refusal of the Home Mission Society to appoint slaveholders as missionaries. For 10 points,\nname this largest Protestant denomination in the United States.",
      "answer": [
        "Southern Baptist Convention",
        "Southern Baptist",
        "Southern Baptism"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "(TIEBREAKER EXAMPLE QUESTION) The admirals who worked for this man included Gil Eanes (ee-AH-nesh) and Antonio Noli.\nHis capture of Ceuta (say-OO-tuh) and leadership of the Order of Christ gave him vast\ndisposable funds, which he used to create the first map that extended to Cape Bojador (boh-hahDOR). For 10 points, name this member of the Aviz Dynasty who never ascended to the\nPortuguese throne but left his mark as a patron of expeditions at the start of the Age of\nExploration.",
      "answer": [
        "Prince Henry the Navigator",
        "Henry the Navigator"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man led the fleet that claimed Cayo Hueso, later known as Key West. He threatened gunboat\ndiplomacy at Uraga with a fleet of four gunboats; in ensuing discussion, he broke the isolationist policy\nof sakoku. The Convention of Kanagawa was signed by, for ten points, what American commodore who\nopened trade with Japan?",
      "answer": [
        "Matthew Perry",
        "M Perry"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A revival of this group that started at one its communities in Watervliet was called the Era of\nManifestations. This religious group uses a heart in a palm to symbolize its founder, Ann Lee’s, teachings.\nAaron Copland’s Appalachian Spring was influenced by this sect’s hymn Simple Gifts. This group broke\nwith the Quakers on lay celibacy. For ten points, name this religious group, nicknamed for its members’\ndancing during prayers.",
      "answer": [
        "Shakers",
        "United Society of Believers in Christ’s Second Appearing"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A group that performed this action in 19th century New York, called the “Big Six,” used a symbolic\nBengal tiger that was adopted by Boss Tweed. Marcus Licinius Crassus led a Roman group that refused\nto perform this action if the customers refused to pay, after which he often purchased the ruins. In\nPhiladelphia, Ben Franklin organized a “bucket brigade” to perform this action. For ten points, name this\npublic service provided by professional groups like the FDNY in New York, which protect structures from\ncombustive destruction.",
      "answer": "firefighting"
    },
    {
      "question": "This plant arrived in the New World thanks to Beatriz de Bobadilla, who gave cuttings of it to\nChristopher Columbus. Boiling houses converted the juice of this plant into a raw material that could\nthen be shaped into a loaf. In the late 18th century, the beet provided a European-based replacement for\nthis crop, which was grown by slave-based plantations throughout the Caribbean. For ten points, name\nthis grass crop that produces stalks rich in sucrose that can be refined into a popular sweetener.",
      "answer": [
        "sugarcane",
        "sugar cane"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This action was avoided by Elvis Presley for two months to film King Creole, but his eventual\nperformance of this action inspired the musical Bye Bye Birdie. Muhammad Ali was banned from boxing\nfor 3 years for refusing to engage in this activity. Britain’s Prince Harry started the Invictus Games for\npeople injured in this activity after he did it in Afghanistan. For ten points, name this action which people\nare drafted into through Selective Service.",
      "answer": [
        "military service",
        "conscription",
        "service"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The production of this item names a group of 18th century nationalist revolutionaries in Italy.\nDuring the Industrial Revolution, the complete deforestation of Britain may have been prevented when\nblacksmiths replaced this item with coke. A companion company founded by Henry Ford produced this\ngood out of byproducts from its car manufacturing; that company is now called Kingsford. For ten points,\nname this hot-burning, wood-based, solid carbon fuel, commonly used in blacksmith forges and barbecue\ngrills.",
      "answer": "charcoal"
    },
    {
      "question": "(TIEBREAKER BONUS QUESTION) In what 1973 conflict did Egyptian forces assault the Bar Lev line while Israel was\nobserved the Jewish day of atonement?",
      "answer": [
        "Yom Kippur Wa",
        "Yom Kippur"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man gathered a small handful of early followers at a deer park near Sarnath. During one sermon, this man was not understood by anyone except Mahakashyapa, who smiled when this man held up a white lotus. After this figure’s enlightenment, he described the Eightfold Path as a method of escaping samsara and attaining nirvana. For ten points, name this religious figure whose teachings form the basis for an Asian religion.",
      "answer": [
        "Siddhartha Gautama",
        "Gautama",
        "the Buddha"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "According to legend, Henry I died by eating too much of this food. The Scania market featured a\nHanseatic League monopoly on this food. The United Kingdom and Iceland fought a so-called war over\none type of this food. Garum was a Roman sauce made from these animals, which are harvested off the\nGrand Banks of Newfoundland. For ten points, name these animals, a primary food source in Scandinavia,\nthat can be caught with a net or rod and reel.",
      "answer": [
        "fish",
        "lampreys",
        "sal fish",
        "herring",
        "cod",
        "fish sauce"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This religion was favored by Gratian, who removed the Altar of Victory in favor of this religion.\nThis religion came into conflict with the cults of Mithras and Sol Invictus. Early branches of this religion\nincluded Arianism and Nestorianism. The Edict of Milan legalized the practice of this religion; earlier,\nmembers of this religion were forced to fight in the Colosseum. For ten points, name this religion that was\npersecuted in Rome until the reign of Constantine the Great.",
      "answer": "Christianity"
    },
    {
      "question": "One member of this program was given the call sign “Chaika,” or “Seagull,” and completed her\nintended action 48 times. The exclamation “poyekhali!” was made at the start of one of this program’s\nmissions; that mission, which began at the Baikonur Cosmodrome, was Vostok 1 and launched in 1961.\nValentina Tereshkova and Yuri Gagarin were members of, for ten points, what Cold War-era program\nthat, in 1957, launched Sputnik into orbit?",
      "answer": [
        "Soviet Union’s space program",
        "Soviet space",
        "Soviet space program",
        "Kosmicheskaya programma SSSR",
        "Russian space program",
        "Russia space",
        "Russia space program"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Philip the Good ordered the construction of one of these objects called Mons Meg. An early metal\nversion of these objects was called the pot-de-fer, and culverins were portable types of these items. The\nHungarian engineer Orban designed a massive one of these objects that malfunctioned and killed him.\nVauban designed star forts to defend against these weapons, which Mehmed II used to destroy the walls\nof Constantinople in 1453. For ten points, name these gunpowder-based artillery pieces.",
      "answer": [
        "cannons",
        "bombards"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Pliny the Younger wrote a letter to Trajan concerning the treatment of these people, the earliest\nreference to these people that wasn’t written by one of them. These people built elaborate catacombs to\nbury their dead and were blamed for a Great Fire by Nero. As a prelude to gladiatorial competitions, these\npeople were forced to fight animals in the arena. For ten points, name these people who were persecuted\nin the Roman Empire for their worship of Jesus.",
      "answer": [
        "Roman Christians",
        "Christians"
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This color names a \"democratic movement\" which supports former Kenyan prime minister\nRaila Odinga (rah-EE-luh oh-DING-guh). A river separating both Namibia and Lesotho from\nSouth Africa is named for this color, which inspired a \"free state\" in pre-union South Africa. For\n10 points, name this color also used for the Dutch royal house and a citrus fruit.",
        "answer": "orange"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The 2004 Orange Revolution protested vote-rigging by Viktor Yanukovych (YAHnik-oh-vitch) in what country?",
        "answer": "Ukraine"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this century, the Ottoman Empire's Tulip Period began with the Treaty of Passarowitz\n(pr. puh-SAH-roe-vits). At the end of this century, the White Lotus Rebellion broke out in\nChina. The Battle of Plassey and the Black Hole of Calcutta took place in this century. For 10\npoints, identify this century in which Britain took control of Canada after the French and Indian\nWar.",
        "answer": "18th, 18th century AD, 1700s"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Battle of Plassey weakened what Islamic dynasty that had ruled in India since\n1526, transferring effective control of most of India to the British East India Company?",
        "answer": "Mughal, Mughal Dynasty"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Alexander Neckham first described the European use of this object, which began in 1190 after\nit was invented in China. This object was used in conjunction with Portolan charts to double the\nVenetian trading season, which previously relied on clear skies for navigation. For 10 points,\nname this navigational device which uses the Earth's magnetic field to point north.",
        "answer": "compass"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What other great navigational problem was solved by John Harrison with the invention\nof the \"Sea Clock\" in 1730, winning a namesake twenty-thousand pound prize?",
        "answer": "longitude, determining a ship's longitude"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In the twentieth century, some groups modified this holiday to use a \"cup of Miriam\" to\nsymbolize women and an orange to symbolize homosexuals. This holiday also changed in the\ntwelfth century, when its service was collected as the \"haggadah\" (pr. hah-GUH-duh). For 10\npoints, name this Jewish holiday on which the \"seder\" (pr. SAY-dur) meal includes matzah\n(MAHT-suh).",
        "answer": [
          "Passover",
          "Pesach"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What book of the Bible, in which Moses leads the Jews out of Egypt, is the focus of\nPassover?",
        "answer": [
          "Book of Exodus",
          "Exodus",
          "Sh'mot"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This religion opposed the Nestorian heresy at the Council of Ephesus (pr. EFF-uh-sis) and\nadvanced the doctrine of \"hypostasis\" (pr. high-PAH-stuh-sis) at the Council of Chalcedon.\nEarlier, this religion challenged the Arian movement at the Council of Nicaea (pr. nigh-SEEuh). For 10 points, name this religion whose early ecumenical councils met under the\nsupervision of the Pope.",
        "answer": [
          "Christianity",
          "Christian",
          "Roman Catholicism",
          "Catholic",
          "Catholicism",
          "Eastern Orthodoxy",
          "Orthodox"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What early Christian martyr is usually said to have been killed for refusing to submit to\nEmperor Claudius II on February 14 of the year 269?",
        "answer": [
          "Saint Valentine",
          "Valentine"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This goddess, who was born from the left eye of Izanagi (pr. ee-zuh-NAH-gee), is\nworshipped at a \"grand shrine\" that is torn down and rebuilt every twenty years. She is believed\nto be the ancestor of the \"tenno,\" who sits on the Chrysanthemum Throne. For 10 points, name\nthis sun goddess, the sister of Susanowo, and the patroness of the Imperial house of Japan.",
        "answer": "Amaterasu"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What Japanese emperor formally renounced his divine status in the \"Jewel Voice\nBroadcast\" of 1945?",
        "answer": [
          "Hirohito",
          "Showa"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This country underwent a religious schism known as the “Raskol” when Patriarch Nikon\nattempted to change the number of fingers used to make the sign of the cross, leading to the split\nof the Old Believers. This country is home to the world’s largest Eastern Orthodox population.\nFor 10 points, name this home country of Kirill I, the Patriarch of Moscow.",
        "answer": "Russia"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Russia’s Dukhobors, another dissenting sect, largely emigrated to what country, where\nreligious diversity is explored in the popular sitcom Little Mosque on the Prairie?",
        "answer": "Canada"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "When asked about violence against followers of this religion, one politician responded, “When a big\ntree falls, the earth shakes.” An empire named for this religion ruled the Punjab under Maharaja Ranjit\nSingh during the first half of the 19th century. For ten points, name this monotheistic religion founded by\nGuru Nanak whose male adherents follow five articles of faith, including the keeping of uncut hair.",
        "answer": [
          "Sikhism",
          "Sikhs"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Another article of Sikhism is the traditional possession of a kirpan, one of these items that, in\n2011, Quebec banned from governmental buildings.",
        "answer": [
          "ceremonial dagger",
          "dagger",
          "ceremonial sword",
          "sword"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this event, paratroopers captured bridges on the River Orne and Saint-Mere-Eglise. The First \nUS Army Group participated in Operation Quicksilver prior to this campaign, and was commanded by\nGeneral Patton. The Canadians were supposed to capture Caen during this operation, and the Americans\nwere assigned to Fortress Cherbourg, part of the Atlantic Wall. For ten points, name this operation, an\nAllied landing on five beaches in Northern France.",
        "answer": [
          "Operation Overlord",
          "Overlord",
          "D-Day",
          "Battle of Normandy",
          "Normandy"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Operation Dragoon, landings after Operation Overlord in the south of France, targeted Toulon\nand this other Mediterranean port, now the second largest French city.",
        "answer": "Marseilles"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The patronage of Gushi Khan increased the power of the holders of this position. A delegate of one\nholder of this position was forced at gunpoint to ratify the Seventeen Point Agreement. Men who hold this\nposition are thought to be incarnations of Avalokiteshvara. The current holder of this position, Tenzin\nGyatso, currently lives in exile in India. For ten points, name this position, the spiritual leader of Tibetan\nBuddhism.",
        "answer": "Dalai Lama"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This other form of Buddhism, which uses koans to teach Buddhist principles, is commonly\npracticed in Japan.",
        "answer": [
          "Zen Buddhism",
          "Zen"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The publication of a pamphlet espousing this concept caused Percy Shelley to be expelled from\nOxford. A 1927 speech at Battersea Town Hall arguing for this concept questioned the idea of everlasting\npunishment as a defect in the moral character of Christ. Bertrand Russell’s “Why I Am Not a Christian”\nargued in favor of, for ten points, what philosophical concept that opposes the existence of gods?",
        "answer": [
          "atheism",
          "not believing in god"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This other philosophical position, championed by Enlightenment-era thinkers like Thomas Paine,\nholds that man can infer the existence of a generally non-intervening god.",
        "answer": "deism"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Brazil bought three of these objects, which led to the nullification of the Pacts of May. The\ndevelopment of objects was partly inspired by Alfred Mahan, and their number and size was limited by the\nWashington Convention. The only remaining one of these vessels is the USS Texas, and the most famous\nvessel of this type is the only one to have sunk a submarine, though she spent the Battle of Jutland in\nport. Steam turbine propulsion and a uniform main battery were the main innovations on, for ten points,\nwhat class of revolutionary, all big gun ship?",
        "answer": "Dreadnought"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Admiral Fisher also championed the uses of torpedoes on these smaller ships for defense against\nsubmarines. These fast ships typically escorted and screened larger ships.",
        "answer": [
          "Destroyers"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Yan Liben’s most famous painting is a long scroll depicting this number of emperors. An area in\nGuangdong which was the only area where Westerners were allowed to trade before the Treaty of Nanjing\nwas known as this number of factories. An amendment with this number was used by the Supreme\nCourt to rule, in Bailey v. Alabama, that a law punishing taking money for unfinished work was akin to\nindentured servitude, which this amendment banned. For ten points, name this number of the first Civil\nRights amendment and the number of original American colonies.",
        "answer": [
          "13",
          "13 Emperors Scroll",
          "13 Factories",
          "13th Amendment",
          "13 original colonies"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What earliest of the Thirteen Classics contains instructions on divination and includes 64\nhexagrams and their interpretations?",
        "answer": [
          "I Ching",
          "Yi Jing",
          "The Book of Changes",
          "The Classic of Changes"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "These devices were used in “596,” an event at Lop Nur. The Dimona Institute in the Negev is widely\nsuspected to be used for manufacturing these devices, which South Africa no longer possesses. “Smiling\nBuddha” was the codename for India’s proof of possession of these devices. A “triad” of submarines,\naircraft, and ballistic missiles are used to deploy, for ten points, what weapons that have not been used in\nwar since 1945, when Harry Truman ordered their use against Japan?",
        "answer": [
          "nuclear weapons",
          "nuclear",
          "atom bombs",
          "hydrogen bombs",
          "atomic bombs"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This treaty, signed in 1968, attempts to prevent the spread of nuclear weapons. It recognizes five\nnations that can have nuclear weapons, but has not been signed by India, Pakistan, or Israel.",
        "answer": [
          "Treaty on the Non-Proliferation of Nuclear Weapons",
          "Non-Proliferation",
          "Non-Proliferation Treaty",
          "NPT"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This religion was spread to Zeila early in its existence, which led to the creation of Adal. This\nreligion spread along the East African coast after Shirazi founded the Kilwa state, attracting merchants\nof this religion who previously traded at Mogadishu. This religion was spread across the Sahara desert by\nBerber traders, and in the Maghreb, it was spread by the Almoravid and Umayyad Dynasties. For ten\npoints, name this religion that spread to Africa from the Middle East after its founding by the prophet\nMuhammad.",
        "answer": [
          "Islam",
          "Sunni Islam"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Umayyads held this type of Islamic state, led by a successor to Muhammad, in North Africa.\nIn 2014, ISIS demanded the allegiance of all Muslims around the world in claiming to have formed this\ntype of state, a move that was roundly criticized and mocked.",
        "answer": "caliphate"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "BREAKAWAY REGIONS",
      "prompt": "Who or what is or was the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Oil-rich African country with capital at Abuja which Biafra broke away from?",
          "answer": "Nigeria"
        },
        {
          "question": "Central Asian nation which has breakaway regions in Abkhazia and South Ossetia and shares\nits name with a U.S. sate?",
          "answer": "Georgia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country where Catalan separatists have been protesting in Barcelona?",
          "answer": "Spain"
        },
        {
          "question": "Middle East ethnic group who have tried to break off from Turkey and have autonomy within\nIraq?",
          "answer": [
            "Kurds",
            "Kurdish"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Country targeted by the Western Sahara independence movement?",
          "answer": "Morocco"
        },
        {
          "question": "Asian country which seized Goa from the Portuguese?",
          "answer": "India"
        },
        {
          "question": "French-speaking West African country where Azawad tried to secede in 2012?",
          "answer": "Mali"
        },
        {
          "question": "Disputed region fought over by Armenia and Azerbaijan in a 1991 war?",
          "answer": "Nagorno-Karabakh"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "HOLY CITIES",
      "prompt": "Which holy city is or was home to...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "the Masjid al-Haram and the Kaaba, the holiest site in Islam?",
          "answer": "Mecca"
        },
        {
          "question": "Solomon’s Temple and the Dome of the Rock in Israel?",
          "answer": "Jerusalem"
        },
        {
          "question": "the birthplace of Jesus and the Church of the Nativity?",
          "answer": "Bethlehem"
        },
        {
          "question": "the childhood home of Jesus in Galilee?",
          "answer": "Nazareth"
        },
        {
          "question": "home to over 1,000 Buddhist shrines built while it was the capital of Japan?",
          "answer": "Kyoto"
        },
        {
          "question": "the burial place of Muhammad, the second-holiest city in Islam?",
          "answer": "Medina"
        },
        {
          "question": "the Golden Temple, which houses the Adi Granth, the Sikh holy scripture?",
          "answer": "Amritsar"
        },
        {
          "question": "the Baha’i World Centre and the Bab’s burial place on Mount Carmel?",
          "answer": "Haifa"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "THE PAPACY",
      "prompt": "In Papal history, what is...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "The city-state within Rome ruled by the Pope?",
          "answer": [
            "Vatican City",
            "Vatican"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The current Pope (2025)?",
          "answer": [
            "Pope Leo XIV",
            "Robert Francis Prevost"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The disciple of Jesus considered to be the first Pope?",
          "answer": [
            "Simon Peter",
            "Saint Peter",
            "Peter"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The term for men who claimed to be Pope, like Clement VII during the Western Schism?",
          "answer": "Antipope"
        },
        {
          "question": "The papal name shared by two 20th century Popes, including one who served only 33 days?",
          "answer": "John Paul"
        },
        {
          "question": "The birth country of the resigned Pope Benedict XVI?",
          "answer": "Germany"
        },
        {
          "question": "The term for legal documents, including Exsurge Domine [EX-ur-gay DOE-mee-nay], which are more\nformal than encyclicals?",
          "answer": [
            "papal bulls",
            "bull"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The 1968 encyclical issued by Paul VI that re-affirmed the rejection of artificial contraception?",
          "answer": [
            "Humanae vitae",
            "Of Human Life",
            "Human Life",
            "On the Regulation of Birth",
            "Regulation of Birth"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "CRASHES",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "City where the Dow Jones average crashed in 1929, starting the Great Depression.",
          "answer": [
            "New York City",
            "New York",
            "NYC"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Company whose Windows operating system shows a “blue screen of death” after it crashes.",
          "answer": "Microsoft"
        },
        {
          "question": "Award ceremony where Crash won Best Picture in 2004.",
          "answer": [
            "Academy Awards",
            "Oscars"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "American company whose 777 jet suffered its first fatal crash with Asiana Flight 214 in San Francisco.",
          "answer": "Boeing"
        },
        {
          "question": "Australian airline whose last fatal crash was in 1951.",
          "answer": "Qantas"
        },
        {
          "question": "Sea north of Sicily over which Itavia Flight 870 may have been shot down in 1980.",
          "answer": [
            "Tyrrhenian Sea",
            "Tyrrhenian"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Commodity, such as the semper augustus whose Dutch speculative market crashed in 1637.",
          "answer": [
            "tulip bulbs",
            "tulip"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "First U.S. space station, which de-orbited in 1979 and crashed in Western Australia.",
          "answer": "Skylab"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "THE INDUSTRIAL REVOLUTION",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "European nation with capital London where the Industrial Revolution began.",
          "answer": [
            "United Kingdom",
            "UK",
            "Great Britain",
            "Britain",
            "England"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Industry where revolution led to increased crop output and a growing population.",
          "answer": [
            "agriculture",
            "farming",
            "farm"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Invention that powered many plants when moving water was unavaliable, invented by James Watt.",
          "answer": "steam engine"
        },
        {
          "question": "The crop sourced from Egypt, India, and the American South, which fueled textile mills.",
          "answer": "cotton"
        },
        {
          "question": "Metal that was tempered into steel and used to build stronger buildings.",
          "answer": "iron"
        },
        {
          "question": "Industrial process used to create steel from otherwise unhelpful smelting byproducts by blowing air\nto remove impurities.",
          "answer": [
            "Bessemer process",
            "Bessemer"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The multi-spindle frame, invented in the 1760s, that allowed for the mass production of yarn.",
          "answer": "spinning jenny"
        },
        {
          "question": "Engineer who designed the Great Western Railway, as well as pre-fabricated hospitals for the Crimean\nWar effort.",
          "answer": [
            "Isambard Kingdom Brunel",
            "Brunel"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "THE CRADLES OF CIVILIZATION",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Age in which the first civilizations developed, often named for a material more primitive than bronze\nor iron.",
          "answer": [
            "Stone Age",
            "Stone",
            "Neolithic Age",
            "Neolithic"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Modern African country where civilization developed around the Nile River.",
          "answer": "Egypt"
        },
        {
          "question": "Modern Asian country where tea drinking developed and civilization grew around the Yellow and\nYangtze rivers.",
          "answer": "China"
        },
        {
          "question": "Civilization that developed around a river in modern Pakistan and included the city of Harappa.",
          "answer": [
            "Indus River Valley civilizaiton",
            "Indus"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Region between the Tigris and Euphrates rivers, in the eastern part of the Fertile Crescent in modern\nIraq.",
          "answer": "Mesopotamia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Civilization that developed in that Iraqi region whose cities included Uruk.",
          "answer": [
            "Sumeria",
            "Sumer"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Anatolian marauders who sailed the Mediterranean, rampaging early cities, but lost the Battle of the\nDelta on the Nile.",
          "answer": "Sea Peoples"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ancient proto-Greek civilization whose fall triggered the Greek Dark Ages.",
          "answer": [
            "Mycenaean culture",
            "Mycenae"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "POLITICAL UPHEAVAL AROUND THE WORLD",
      "prompt": "Which country was the site of the coup d’etat of...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Ioannis Metaxas, who restored order to the streets of Athens in 1936?",
          "answer": "Greece"
        },
        {
          "question": "A CIA-MI5 alliance that installed a pro-western Shah in Tehran?",
          "answer": "Iran"
        },
        {
          "question": "anti-Erdogan [air-doh-wan] protesters, who were fought back by tanks in Istanbul in 2016?",
          "answer": "Turkey"
        },
        {
          "question": "1945’s Kyujo incident, in which officers wanted to stop this country from surrendering World War II?",
          "answer": "Japan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Hafez al-Assad, who established a Baathist government in 1963 that is now led by his son, Bashar?",
          "answer": "Syria"
        },
        {
          "question": "Getulio Vargas, who started the Estado Novo dictatorship?",
          "answer": "Brazil"
        },
        {
          "question": "Generals seeking to enforce lese majeste [lez mah-jest-ay] laws that protected Rama IX [ninth] in\nSoutheast Asia?",
          "answer": "Thailand"
        },
        {
          "question": "Alberto Fujimori, who defeated the communist Shining Path insurgency in South America?",
          "answer": "Peru"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "MORMONISM",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Modern U.S. state that Mormons settled, founding Salt Lake City, after fleeing persecution.",
          "answer": "Utah"
        },
        {
          "question": "Founder of Mormonism and mentor of Brigham Young.",
          "answer": [
            "Joseph Smith",
            "Smith"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "State whose city of Nauvoo was the site of the founder’s 1844 assassination.",
          "answer": "Illinois"
        },
        {
          "question": "Name of the religious movement, shortened to LDS, that subscribes to Mormon theology.",
          "answer": [
            "Latter Day Saints Movement",
            "Latter Day Saint",
            "Church of Jesus Christ of Latter Day Saints",
            "Jesus Christ of Latter Day Saints"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Mormon practice of keeping multiple wives, which caused tension with American settlers.",
          "answer": "polygamy"
        },
        {
          "question": "Material on which the Book of Mormon was passed to humanity from the angel Moroni.",
          "answer": [
            "golden plates",
            "gold"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Unrecognized state founded by Mormon settlers that covered most of the Mexican Cession.",
          "answer": [
            "State of Deseret",
            "Deseret"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "1857 massacre of the Fancher-Baker party by Mormons that led to conflict between the Mormons and\nthe U.S.",
          "answer": [
            "Mountain Meadows Massacre",
            "Mountain Meadows"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "INDIAN OCEAN TRADE",
      "prompt": "A system of trade in the Indian Ocean...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Linked the subcontinent, around 1 AD, to which European empire that spanned the Mediterranean?",
          "answer": [
            "Roman Empire",
            "Roman",
            "Rome"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was manipulated by which European nation that was the first to sail to India?",
          "answer": [
            "Kingdom of Portugal",
            "Portugal"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Involved ports in what region west of India, home to the Safavid Empire and namesake of a gulf south\nof it?",
          "answer": "Persia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Used the winds generated by what phenomenon that brings heavy rainfall to portions of India?",
          "answer": "monsoons"
        },
        {
          "question": "Visited which country on the tip of the Arabian peninsula, the site of a trading base at Muscat?",
          "answer": "Oman"
        },
        {
          "question": "Included the use of which massive Chinese ships used by Zheng He on his voyages?",
          "answer": "junk"
        },
        {
          "question": "Visited the East African coast, populated by speakers of which language, a mix of Arabic, Bantu, and\nother native languages?",
          "answer": "Swahili"
        },
        {
          "question": "Passed through which strait at the end of the Malayan Peninsula, which was dominated by a namesake\nsultanate?",
          "answer": [
            "Straits of Malacca",
            "Malacca"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "NEW WORLD PIRACY",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Items displayed on the classic “Jolly Roger” pirate flag.",
          "answer": [
            "bones",
            "skull",
            "crossbones",
            "skull and crossbones",
            "skull and bones"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Alcoholic beverage made from distilled sugarcane juice that pirates drank mixed with water as\n“bumbo” or “grog.”",
          "answer": "rum"
        },
        {
          "question": "Disease caused by a lack of Vitamin C that pirates could avoid by eating limes.",
          "answer": "scurvy"
        },
        {
          "question": "Sea dominated by 17th century pirates from Cuba to the Lesser Antilles to South America.",
          "answer": [
            "Caribbean Sea",
            "Caribbean"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Island in that sea where pirates docked at Port Royal. It’s now a country with capital Kingston.",
          "answer": "Jamaica"
        },
        {
          "question": "Pirate who commanded the Queen Anne’s Revenge and died in a shootout in North Carolina.",
          "answer": [
            "Blackbeard",
            "Edward Teach",
            "Teach",
            "Edward Thatch",
            "Thatch"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Pirate who captured the Quedagh Merchant and supposedly left a massive buried treasure, according\nto Robert Louis Stevenson and others.",
          "answer": [
            "Captain William Kidd",
            "Kidd"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Famous pirate island just north of Haiti, where Henry Morgan hired some of his crew. A “Dry” island\ngroup off the Florida Keys shares its name.",
          "answer": [
            "Tortuga",
            "Dry Tortugas"
          ]
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The founder of this religion is depicted reacting to sweetness in the painting The Vinegar\nTasters. Mystics within this religion formed the Five Pecks of Rice Society, which formed a\nbreakaway state that followed the (20 pts) ",
        "\"Celestial Master.\" This religion was believed to be\nfounded by a 900-year-old man who was forced to write down The Book of the (10 pts) ",
        "Way\nbefore leaving for the West. For 10 points, name this traditional, non-Confucian religion of\nChina."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Daoism",
        "Taoism"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Mehmet Ali Ağca attempted to assassinate someone holding this position. Eugenio Pacelli\nwas criticized for his silence over the Holocaust while he held it. One of these people\ncondemned (20 pts) ",
        "contraception in Humanae Vitae. Karol Wojtyla was the first non- (10 pts) ",
        "Italian\nto hold this position in over 400 years, and Jorge Bergoglio became the first non-European in\nover 1,000 years when he succeeded Benedict XVI. For 10 points, name this head of the Roman\nCatholic Church."
      ],
      "answer": "Pope"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In the third century AD, this building was the home of a red idol with a golden right\nhand that depicted Hubal. The construction of this building was traditionally attributed to (20 pts) ",
        "Ibrahim, who journeyed with his son Ishmael to a spot near the Well of Zamzam. This\nbuilding was cleared of idols near the start of the (10 pts) ",
        "Islamic era and is now the destination of\nthe hajj, or pilgrimage. For 10 points, name this black, square building around which Mecca is\nbuilt."
      ],
      "answer": "the Kaaba"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) An event which began on this ship provided the nickname for Molly Brown. Frederick\nFleet was unable to avert disaster aboard this ship despite performing adequate lookout\nduties, and many of its (20 pts) ",
        "survivors were picked up by the Carpathia. Edward J. Smith\ncaptained this ship on behalf of the (10 pts) ",
        "White Star Line. For 10 points, name this ship whose\nattempt to make good time to New York caused it to hit an iceberg and sink in the north Atlantic\nin April 1912."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "RMS Titanic",
        "Titanic"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) (TIEBREAKER EXAMPLE QUESTION) These people were sought out due to the new doctrine of \"limpieza de sangre\" (pr. leempee-EY-zuh day SAHN-gray), or \"cleanliness of blood.\" These people were given a\nderogatory nickname meaning (20 pts) ",
        "\"pig\" and were subject to the public \"auto de fe\" (pr.\nOW-toe deh FAY) if found. Tomas de Torquemada gave these people three months to leave (10 pts) ",
        "Spain in 1492. For 10 points, name these people whom the Inquisition sought to find\nsurvivals of within the \"conversos\" community."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Spanish former Jews",
        "Jews",
        "secret Jews"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A road extending from Castrum Truentinum to the Aurelian Walls of Rome was named\nfor this substance, whose transportation was the impetus for building some of the oldest\nknown (20 pts) ",
        "roads. This substance was traded to the north in exchange for gold from the (10 pts) ",
        "African interior, especially by the Ghana empire. For 10 points, identify this formerly valuable\nsubstance which can now be easily retrieved from natural sources such as seawater and is often\niodized."
      ],
      "answer": "salt"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 1855, Napoleon III commissioned a classification system for this commodity, produced\nby Haut-Brion and Chateau Margaux. Prominent (20 pts) ",
        "growing regions for this product\ninclude France’s “golden slope,” though the 1976 Judgment of Paris proved the quality of (10 pts) ",
        "California’s production of varieties like Cabernet Sauvignon. For ten points, name this alcoholic\nbeverage produced in Burgundy and Bordeaux from grapes."
      ],
      "answer": "wine"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One teacher of this religion, Bhadrabahu, was the spiritual advisor of Chandragupta\nMaurya, who converted to this religion after his reign. The (20 pts) ",
        "purported founder of this\nreligion was born with the name Vardhamana and is considered the last (10 pts) ",
        "tirthankara.\nGandhi’s concept of satyagraha was inspired by this religion’s concept of ahimsa. For ten points, name\nthis nonviolent Indian religion founded by Mahavira."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Jainism",
        "Jain"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This crop is freeze dried and eaten as chuno [choo-nyo] by the Quechua people, and\nhas been since at least the 13th century. This crop arrived in Europe via Spanish sailors\nreturning from the (20 pts) ",
        "Andes Mountains in Peru. An 1845 infestation of phytophthora\n[fi-tow-tho-ra] caused a serious (10 pts) ",
        "blight on this crop, dooming over a million people to famine in\nIreland. For ten points, name this starch, densely nutritious food that, in American cuisine, is commonly\nbaked, mashed, or cooked into French fries."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "potatoes",
        "potato"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) (TIEBREAKER EXAMPLE QUESTION) This man was able to return to his hometown following negotiations with the tribe of the Quraish (pr. koo-RYE-eesh) at the Treaty of Hudaybiyyah (pr. hoo-dah-BEE-ah). (20 pts) ",
        "This man was buried next to an empty tomb which is reserved for the returned Jesus after he died in the home of his wife Aisha (pr. eye-EE-shuh). (10 pts) ",
        "For ten points, name this man who received a \"recitation\" from the angel Jibril (pr. jib-REEL) which became the Quran, and was the founder of Islam."
      ],
      "answer": "Muhammad"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A use of this technology by the Kingdom of Mysore was refined by William Congreve.\nThe introduction of another form of this technology allowed Hongi Hika to win inter-tribal\nwars among the (20 pts) ",
        "Maori on New Zealand. Ottoman Janissaries were trained in using this\ntechnology under Mehmed the Conqueror. (10 pts) ",
        "Guy Fawkes’s failed plot to destroy Parliament\ninvolved barrels of, for ten points, what volatile material, a mixture of saltpeter, sulfur, and charcoal\nwhose invention in 9th century China led to the development of hand cannons and modern projectile\nweapons?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "gunpowder",
        "black powder",
        "Congreve rockets",
        "rocket",
        "Musket War",
        "Musket"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) An inflammatory letter by Leo of Ohrid helped spark this event. The Council of\nFerrara-Florence tried to reverse this event after John VIII Palaiologos needed help against\nthe (20 pts) ",
        "Ottoman Empire. The Massacre of the Latins worsened the effects of this event\nand led to the Sack of Thessalonica in revenge. The Norman conquest of southern Italy led\nto a call for help that began this event. This event began when a delegation refused to grant\nCerularius the title of (10 pts) ",
        "Ecumenical Patriarch, which resulted in a mutual excommunication. For\nten points, name this split between Roman Catholicism and the Eastern Orthodox church."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Great Schism",
        "Schism of 1054"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Anti-British activists of this religion in the early-20th century were known as “LalBal-Pal.” A speech beginning “sisters and brothers of America” introduced this religion\nto America at the 1893 Parliament of the World’s Religions and was given by (20 pts) ",
        "Swami\nVivekananda. A liberation from the birth-rebirth cycle sought in this religion is known\nas moksha. Opposition to this religion’s (10 pts) ",
        "Brahmanist caste system led to the development of\nJainism and Buddhism. For ten points, name this predominant religion of India."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Hinduism",
        "Hindu"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During this time period, a hunger march called the Jarrow Crusade marched to London,\nwhere the House of Commons completely ignored them. In this time period, Francis\nTownsend proposed a two-percent transaction tax to fund an (20 pts) ",
        "Old Age Revolving\nPension Plan. The Smoot Hawley Act may have worsened the effects of this time period, in\nwhich vagrants were arrested for (10 pts) ",
        "“riding the rails” and living in Hoovervilles. For ten points,\nname this period of history that followed the 1929 Wall Street Crash and adversely affected economies\naround the world."
      ],
      "answer": "Great Depression"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During an expedition to the Azores, this man captured the Madre de Deus treasure\nship. This man failed to heed a pardon for trying to overthrow King James I in the Main\nPlot, which later cost him his life. (20 pts) ",
        "John White was sent to govern over a “lost colony”\nthis man founded, in which the word (10 pts) ",
        "“Croatoan” was the only hint of where the settlers\ndisappeared. For ten points, name this founder of Roanoke colony who shares his name with the capital\nof North Carolina."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Sir Walter Raleigh",
        "Raleigh"
      ]
    }
  ]
}